Guide to the Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island Lantern Slides PHOTOS.024
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Union Label and Service Trades Council of Greater New York and Long Island Lantern Slides
circa 1912-1921
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Central Union Label Council of New York City
AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council
PHOTOS.024
1 Linear Feet in 3 media boxes
In 1911, the Union Label Trades Department of the American Federation of Labor (AFL) chartered the Central Union Label Council of New York City. The Union Label Council, and later its state counterpart, focused on lobbying, service and publicity for union-labeled goods produced by union members. The collection consists of 218 3"x 4" lantern slides. The majority of these slides are text captions from a lantern slide show created by the Central Labor Union Council to promote the creation and use of union labels, or are images of the union labels themselves. The remainder of the collection is groups of lantern slides –variously text, cartoons, or photographs--on a range of different topics, including photographs of the Lawrence, Massachusetts textile strike of 1912 and other news events of 1912, photographs of ballots, candidates, and campaign literature for some elections held in 1921 in New York City and New York State, World War I-era political cartoons from newspapers, and text of jokes and humorous sayings.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection were donated by the New York City Central Labor Council, AFL-CIO. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1950.182 and NPA.1989.005.
Arrangement
Arranged in one series numerically by (archivist-assigned) sleeve numbers.
Historical/Biographical Note
In 1911, the Union Label Trades Department of the American Federation of Labor (AFL) chartered the Central Union Label Council of New York City. Like its parent body, which had been established by Samuel Gompers in 1909, the New York City Union Label Council was dedicated to "a more systematic and thorough agitation and demand for union-made and particularly union label products, and for the patronage of union organizations issuing them." The Union Label Council, and later its state counterpart, focused on lobbying, service and publicity, all in the interest of union-labeled goods produced by members of craft unions. In 1935, the Union Label Trades and Services Department of the AFL chartered a Union Label Trades and Services Department for the state of New York. The state organization called conventions annually and published the Union Label News. In 1959, the New York Council expanded its jurisdiction to Nassau and Suffolk Counties.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 218 3 "x 4" lantern slides. The majority are text captions from a lantern slide lecture created by the Central Labor Union Council to promote the creation and use of union labels (slide numbers 151 through 182) and images of the labels themselves--created by labor unions to identify goods and services produced or performed by the unions—or images that incorporate the labels that exhort viewers to purchase products with the labels (slide numbers 40 through 130a, and slides 10 through 22 and 25 through 38, which include duplicates). Both images of the labels of images incorporating the labels have been designated: "Union label" in this collection; they represent dozens of unions (many now defunct). The slide lecture and union label groups are mostly are black and white, although some tinted and colored slides also are present, and both date from ca. 1918-1921. They may also have originally been integrated into one slide show.
The remainder of the collection includes groups of lantern slides of text, cartoons, and photographs on various topics, including following: photographs of the famous Lawrence, Massachusetts textile strike of 1912 that was led by the Industrial Workers of the World (slides 131 through 144); photographs of other news events of 1912 distributed by the commercial wire service company American Press Association (slides 145 through 150); reproductions of World War I-era political cartoons mainly from the New York Tribune newspaper (slides 1 through 4); a series of topical printed jokes titled "Fletcher's Weekly Screen Jazz" (most in this particular group relate to women) that were projected on screens as part of vaudeville shows, ca. World War I-era (slides 109 through 213); text of "comical sayings" from the New York Evening World newspaper ca. World War I (slides 214 through 218); a mix of photographs (some appear to be hand-colored) of ballots, candidates, and campaign literature for some of the New York City and New York State elections of 1921 (slides 183 through 193); and miscellaneous text captions from another (unidentified) lantern slide show, a photograph titled, "Bakery in a Living Room, Early 20th Century" (slides 5 through 9); a comic cartoon showing honeymooners at Niagra Falls, a cartoon about World War I (slide number 39) and another comical saying (slides 23 and 24).
Textile Workers' Strike, Lawrence, Mass., 1912; Elections -- New York (State) -- New York.; Elections |z New York (State).; Lantern slides; Union labels; American Labor Press Association; Industrial Workers of the World; AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council
- Newspaper cartoon from New York Tribune on food shortages in Europe (Box 1, Item 1)
- Newspaper cartoon from New York Tribune on soldier going to war, 1918 (Box 1, Item 2)
- Newspaper cartoon from Des Moines Register on peace negotiations, World War I (Box 1, Item 3)
- Newspaper cartoon from New York Tribune cartoon on "Tomboy Taylor" (Box 1, Item 4)
- "Working Conditions: Bakery in Living Room Early 20th Century" (Box 1, Item 5)
- "Grocery Stores and Markets Which Harbour and Feed Flies Should not be Patronized. They Spread Disease." (Box 1, Item 6)
- "Value of Each Day a Boy Goes to School" (Box 1, Item 7)
- "Annual Red Cross Roll Call, Nov. 11-12, 1921" (Box 1, Item 8)
- "From 'The New France'" (Box 1, Item 9)
- Union label: Coopers International Union (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 10)
- Union label: Typographical Union (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 11)
- Union label: International Ladies Garment Workers Union (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 12)
- Union label: Tobacco Workers International Union (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 13)
- Union label: Deutsch - Amerikanische Typographia (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 14)
- Union label: International Union of Slate Workers (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 15)
- Union label: International P.P. Union of North America (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 16)
- Union label: Working Men's Cooperative Publishing Assn. (The Evening Call) (Box 1, Item 17)
- Union label: Amalgamated Meatcutters (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 18)
- Union label: International Brotherhood of Paper Makers (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 19-20)
- Union label: "J.H.V." (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 20)
- Union label: National Print Cutters Association of America, AFL (Box 1, Item 22)
- Cartoon (Honeymooners at Niagara Falls) (Box 1, Item 23)
- Comical saying (Box 1, Item 24)
- Union Label lecture (duplicate) (Box 1, Item 25-38)
- Cartoon -- World War I era (Box 1, Item 39)
- Union label: United Powder & High Explosive Workers of America (Box 1, Item 40)
- Union label: American Federation of Musicians (Box 1, Item 41)
- Union label: International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (Box 1, Item 42)
- Union label: Amalgamated Association of Street & Electrical Railway Employees of America (Box 1, Item 43)
- Union label: Brotherhood of Boiler Makers, Iron Ship Builders & Helpers of America (Box 1, Item 44)
- Union label: Hotel & Restaurant Employees International Alliance, Bartenders International League of America, AFL (Box 1, Item 45)
- Union label: International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees, Local 306 (Box 1, Item 46)
- Union label: International Association of Amalgamated Sheet Metal Workers (Box 1, Item 47)
- Union label: United Hatters of North America (Box 1, Item 48)
- Union label: American Federation of Labor (Box 1, Item 49)
- Union label: "BTT" (Box 1, Item 50)
- Union label: Marble Polishers (Box 1, Item 51)
- Union label: Amalgamated Meatcutters and Butcher Workmen (Box 1, Item 52)
- Union label: International Glove Workers of America (Box 1, Item 53)
- Union label: Retail Clerks International Protective Association (Box 1, Item 54)
- Union label: International Brotherhood of Tip Printers (Box 1, Item 55-56)
- Union label: United Hatters of America (Box 1, Item 57)
- Union label: United Cloth Hats & Cap Makers of North America (Box 1, Item 58)
- Union label: United Garment Workers of America (Box 1, Item 59-61)
- Union label: United Garment Workers of America, Special Order Clothing Branch (Box 1, Item 61)
- Union label: Journeyman Tailors Union of America (Box 1, Item 62)
- Union label: International Ladies Garment Workers Union (Box 1, Item 63)
- Union label: International Union Shirt, Waist & Laundry Workers (Box 1, Item 64)
- Union label: United Textile Workers of America (Box 1, Item 65)
- Union label: United Textile Workers of America (Box 1, Item 66)
- Union label: International Longshoreman's Association (Box 1, Item 67)
- Union label: International Woodcarvers Association (Box 1, Item 68)
- Union label: Amalgamated Woodworkers International Union of America (Box 1, Item 69)
- Union label: United Brotherhood of Carpenters & Joiners of America (Box 1, Item 70)
- Union label: Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators & Paperhangers of America (Box 1, Item 71)
- Union label: "O.P. & C.F.I.A." (plasterers) (Box 1, Item 72)
- Union label: Amalgamated Meatcutters & Butcher Workers of North America, Local 19 (Box 3, Item 73)
- Union label: Coopers International Union (Box 1, Item 74)
- Union label: Coopers International Union, No.1 (Box 2, Item 75)
- Union label: Wood Wire & Metal International Union (Box 2, Item 76)
- Union label: Lathers (Box 2, Item 77)
- Union label: International Association of Marble Workers (Box 2, Item 78)
- Union label: International Shingle Weavers Union of America (Box 2, Item 79)
- Union label: International Association of Machinists (Box 2, Item 80-81)
- Union label: International Brotherhood of Stationary Firemen (Box 2, Item 82)
- Union label: International Union of Steam Engineers (Box 2, Item 83)
- Union label: International Molders Union of North America (Box 2, Item 84)
- Union label: International Union of the United Brewery Workmen of America (Box 2, Item 85)
- Union label: International Broom & Brush Makers Union (Box 2, Item 86)
- Union label: Brush Makers International Union (Box 2, Item 87-88)
- Union label: Sawsmiths Union of North America (Box 2, Item 89)
- Union label: International Jewelry Workers Union of America (Box 2, Item 90)
- Union label: Metal Polishers, Buffers, Platers, Brass & Silver Workers Union of North America (Box 2, Item 91)
- Union label: Metal Polishers, Buffers, Platers, Molders, Brass & Silver Workers Union of North America (Box 2, Item 92)
- Union label: Travelers Goods & Leather Novelty Workers International Union of America (Box 2, Item 93)
- Union label: Leather Workers International Union (Box 2, Item 94)
- Union label: United Association of Plumbers, Gas-Fitters, Steam-Fitters & Steam Fitters Helpers (Box 2, Item 95)
- Union label: Stone Mounters International Union (Box 2, Item 96)
- Union label: Brush Makers International Union (Box 2, Item 97)
- Union label: Boot & Shoe Workers Union, Local 160, Woman's Auxiliary (Box 2, Item 98)
- Union label: Upholsters, International Union of North America (Box 2, Item 99)
- Union label: International Union of Slate Workers (Box 2, Item 100)
- Union label: International Steel & Copper Plate Printers Union of North America (Box 2, Item 101)
- Union label: Hotel & Restaurant Employees International Alliance (Box 2, Item 102)
- Union label: Hotel & Restaurant Employees International Alliance, Bartenders International League (Box 2, Item 103)
- Union label: Tobacco Workers International Union (Box 2, Item 104)
- Union label: Allied Printing Trades Council, New York City (Box 2, Item 105)
- Union label: NPCAA, AFL (National Print Cutters Assn. of America (?)) (Box 2, Item 106)
- Union label: Ink Workers of America, Under the Jurisdiction of I.P.P. & A.U. of N.A. (Box 2, Item 107)
- Union label: Deutsch - Amerikanische Typographia (Box 2, Item 108)
- Union label: Typographical Union (Box 2, Item 109)
- Union label: International Photo Engineers Union (Box 2, Item 110-111)
- Union label: International P.P. Union of North America (Box 2, Item 112)
- Union label: M.P. & C.M. of U.S., AFL (Box 2, Item 113)
- Union label: International Brotherhood of Paper Makers (Box 2, Item 114-115)
- Union label: International Brotherhood of Bookbinders (Box 2, Item 116-117)
- Union label: Workingmen's Cooperative Publishing Association (Box 2, Item 118)
- Union label: Journeyman Horseshoer's Union (Box 2, Item 119)
- Union label: "J.H.U." (Box 2, Item 120)
- Union label: "I.B.B.H." (Box 2, Item 121)
- Union label: National Print Cutters Association of America, Local 1, AFL (Box 2, Item 122)
- Union label: International Alliance of Bill Posters & Billers of America (Box 2, Item 123)
- Union label: Actors Union of America (Box 2, Item 124)
- Union label: Theatrical Federation of Greater N.Y. (IATSE, AFM) (Box 2, Item 125)
- Union label: International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees & Moving Picture Machine Operators of the U.S. & Canada (Box 2, Item 126)
- Union label: International Alliance of Theatrical Stage, Local 306, Moving Picture Machine Operators (Box 2, Item 127)
- Union label: Piano & Organ Workers International Union of America (Box 2, Item 128-129)
- Union label: "Amalgamated Association of I.S. & T.W. of N.A." (Box 2, Item 130)
- Union label: American Wire Weavers' Protective Association (Box 2, Item 130A)
- 1912 - Lawrence, Massachusetts Textile Strike (Box 2, Item 131-144)
- American Press Association: Assassination Attempt on Theodore Roosevelt (Box 2, Item 145-147)
- American Press Association: Powder Explosion, Tampico, Mexico (Box 3, Item 148)
- American Press Association: Launching of the Battleship New York, President Taft in Attendance (Box 3, Item 149)
- American Press Association: View from Riverside Drive of Battleships on Hudson, President Taft Reviewing Ships (Box 3, Item 150)
- Union Label lecture (Box 3, Item 151-168)
- Union Label lecture (duplicate) (Box 3, Item 169)
- Union Label lecture (Box 3, Item 170-178)
- Union Label lecture (colored slide) (Box 3, Item 179-182)
- 1921 New York City Election - Mayoral Election Ballot:John F. Hylan, Henry H. Curran, Jacob Panken (Box 3, Item 183)
- 1921 New York City Election - Mayoral Election: John F. Hylan (Box 3, Item 184)
- 1921 New York City Election - Mayoral Election: Henry H. Curran (Box 3, Item 185)
- 1921 New York City Election - Mayoral Election: Jacob Panken (Box 3, Item 186)
- 1921 New York City Election - Mayoral Election: Hylan Wins in Landslide (Box 3, Item 187)
- 1921 New York City Election for Comptroller: Charles L. Craig, Democratic Candidate (Box 3, Item 188)
- 1921 New York City Election - Board of Aldermen Ballot: G. Murray Hulbert (Democratic Party); Vincent Gilroy (Republican Party), James Oneal (Socialist Party), Abraham Lefkowitz (Farm and Labor Party) (Box 3, Item 189)
- 1921 New York City Election – Aldermen Election: Isaac Frank (Box 3, Item 190)
- 1921 New York City Election – Aldermen Election: Murray Hulbert (Box 3, Item 191)
- 1921 New York State Election – Aldermen Election: Justice of Supreme Court Candidate: Harry E. Lewis (Box 3, Item 192)
- 1921 New York State Election – Election, New York, County Judge: Wm R. Bayes (Box 3, Item 193)
- "Fletcher's Weekly Screen Jazz" ("Jazz-ical Jokelets on Timely Topics") (Box 3, Item 194-213)
- New York Evening World - Comical Sayings, WWI Era (Box 3, Item 218)